Therapy is not evaluated on a merit-based system,
...where if you put in enough effort,
...you'll get an 'A+',
...and then I'll write you a letter recommendation.
That's not what we do here.
♪♪
Okay. Hi, everybody!
Today we're doing another '5 Things'
...style video,
...um...
This one, I think, is gonna be kind of fun,
...as if they all haven't been fun.
So we're talking about
...five things that your therapist wants you to know.
I'm really excited about this.
I've had this list in the works for a little while,
...and, so...
Yeah.
I guess that's it.
We'll just get into it.
Okay, so:
Thing number one that I want to talk about
...is that:
When I say this, what I mean is that,
...as a therapist, sometimes
...we will make educated guesses
...or ask questions,
...and kind of like,
...the way that I always phrase it is:
"I wonder if it's X, Y, or Z."
Basically what I'm getting at is that, as a therapist,
...sometimes we make educated guesses
...based on the information that you give us.
That does not mean that
we're gonna be upset or pissy,
...um, or irritated at you,
...if you're like,
"No, that's not it."
Sometimes I might disagree with a client
...where, like,
...I'll see a behavior pattern happening,
...and say, like,
"I wonder if there's a pattern
to this kind of behavior,"
...and they'll say, "No."
I'm like, "Okay,"
"...that's fine!"
That's what I mean here,
...and that's one of the other things
that's really important here is that:
A good therapist,
...even if they disagree with you or if they feel like,
"Mmm, maybe you don't fully see that yet,"
...a good therapist shouldn't argue with you,
...because it's not about our ego.
My
...self-worth
...is not tied up in being right
...or having, um,
...an educated guess be correct
...all of the time.
And so,
...especially when your therapist
asks you a question about,
"I wonder if this is because of this,"
...it's okay for you to say,
"No, that's not it at all,"
...or for you to be like,
"No, that's not why I do that."
"That's not what I was thinking."
"That's not what I was feeling."
...especially...
So, yeah. Your therapist really doesn't,
...or shouldn't,
...give a shit
...about being right or wrong.
Uh, our job here is to help you
...and to make sure that you are moving
...in the direction you want to move.
Okay.
Thing number two:
...especially...
This comes up a lot when people are like,
"Oh my gosh, I'm all over the place," or
"I'm talking too fast," or
"None of these things are related," or
"I'm not making any sense."
None of that is annoying.
It doesn't bother me,
...especially in an intake session
...where, like,
...this is the first time that we've talked about
...your issues and your stuff.
It's totally okay
...for you to jump back and forth
...between this thing and
that thing and then this thing,
...and, like,
...all over the place, right?
Because, especially for people
who are new to therapy,
...you've never done this before.
And also too,
...having your thoughts organized in, like, an
'easily digestible format'
...is not your job.
My job as a therapist
...is to catch the things that
people throw at me all day.
And so even if you are being super all-over-the-place,
...very disorganized, or chaotic,
...like,
...please understand that
...you are not the first person to do that to me today,
...and you will absolutely not be the last.
So, again,
...it's my job as a therapist
...to pick up
...all of the chaotic pieces that people have.
And sometimes that's really
the purpose of therapy too,
...is for a person to lay out
...all of the disorganized, chaotic, and confusing pieces
...so that you can then
...organize them and put them
in order and make sense of them,
...and kind of figure out,
"How do I feel about this?"
"What's going on with this?"
So, no, you're never annoying to us,
...you're not bothering me,
...it isn't upsetting or, like,
...shocking to me
...when somebody is all over the place
...and is having a hard time
making sense of their thoughts.
That's literally what we do all day,
...and so please know that
we are never annoyed at you
...or frustrated by that, like, ever,
...or else we shouldn't be good therapists,
...or not.
Okay.
Thing number three:
It's okay
...if the therapeutic relationship is not a good fit.
The caveat with this
...is that if it's not a good fit,
...please just say something,
...because
...this has happened sometimes
...where I, as the therapist,
...have felt like, "Maybe this isn't a good fit."
"We don't align."
"I'm not the right therapist for this job."
And so obviously I'm comfortable voicing that,
...bringing that into the room,
and letting a person know
...I think it would be wise
...for me to refer you out.
But a lot of times,
...when a client
...feels like it's not a good fit,
...or, like, things aren't jiving,
...um, what will happen is that they will just
...ghost you.
[chuckles]
They will just disappear into the night,
...which is fine.
It's not a big deal,
...we're not, like,
...you know, at least I am not mad when this happens.
But if you feel like it's not a good fit,
...that's totally okay.
That happens.
That's a normal part of therapy.
Therapy is deeply personal,
...and so it's important for you to vibe
with your therapist on some level.
But if you feel like it's not a good fit,
...just say something.
Any good therapist would be like,
"Okay, great! So glad that you brought it up."
"If it's important to you,"
"...we can work through it and see if we can, maybe,"
"...adjust some things, or if I can adjust my approach"
"...to make it feel like a better fit."
"Or, if you prefer, I can refer you out"
"...and give you resources to"
"...help you along your journey
to find another therapist."
But it is...
...so much more paperwork for me,
...like, I have to make
...several phone calls,
...and then I have to document all of this stuff
...to make sure that I can prove that
...I didn't go to you.
So if it's not a good fit,
...just say something.
Really, if you can avoid it,
...I know that it's uncomfortable and it's hard,
...and it's, like, kind of a shady conversation to have,
...but if you can avoid it,
...please don't go to your therapist.
That's, like, the [laughs] number one thing
...that is, like, an unnecessary paperwork generator?
I guess this one is sort of twofold,
...but number three is that:
If it's not a good fit, that's okay,
...but also, like, please just say something.
Okay.
Thing number four
...is that:
Therapists are
...never allowed to be their clients' friends anyways,
...but also, sometimes people have this perception
...that being in therapy means that
...you're paying someone to be your friend
...or to listen to you.
That's not the case,
...especially when people talk about,
...you know, "You're just paying
somebody to agree with you."
Like,
...no.
No, no, no.
My job as a therapist is not to just gas people up
...or be like, "Yeah, you're so right"
...all the time.
That's not clinically appropriate,
...and sometimes people really do need a space
...to grow into the realization that, like,
"Oh, this thing I've been doing is kind of problematic"
"...and maybe I should stop."
And you know, again, there's a way to do that
...with kindness and compassion.
But my job as a therapist is not to be
...somebody's friend.
That's highly unethical anyways.
We've talked about this before on the channel,
...but I'm not allowed to be my client's friend.
In no capacity
...am I allowed to have a relationship with a client,
...a former client,
...ever.
Like, even after
...thirty years have passed
...and this person is no longer a client of mine.
I am not allowed to be their friend.
This is for a very specific and ethical reason.
And so,
...your therapist is a paid professional to help you,
...and the relationship is very personal,
...it is very intimate, and so
...there is kind of a connection
...that happens between a therapist and a client.
But, again,
...you're not paying us to be your friend,
...or to agree with you all the time,
...or just to be somebody who is,
...like, lying to you
...and just, like, endlessly supportive.
That's not the purpose of therapy.
And so...
Yeah.
There you go.
Okay.
Number five is that:
...you cannot get,
...or at least with me as a therapist,
...you cannot get a '100%'
...or an 'A-plus' in therapy.
That's not what we do here.
Therapy is not evaluated on a merit-based system,
...where if you put in enough effort,
...you'll get an 'A+'
...and then I'll write you a letter recommendation.
Doesn't work that way.
Therapy is about you
...and the progress that you want to make.
And so...
You can, like, 'succeed' in therapy,
...in the sense that,
...if you're
...meeting the goals that you've set for yourself
...or you're making progress on the things
you wanted to make progress on.
That feels good,
...that's exciting, and that's, you know,
...like a goal reached,
...but I'm never gonna give you a '100%'
...or an 'A+'
...and tell you, like,
"Good job, kid. You're done,"
...because that it doesn't work that way, first of all.
None of us will ever be done growing,
...and so the-
...there's no
'100%' bar
...that you can reach in therapy anyways.
But also, it's just not appropriate,
...because, again,
...it's not about me.
What that does is place value on
...my opinion of your progress,
...and that's not the point.
Some people do really want
...the approval of their therapist,
...and they want to feel like their therapist
...is proud of them and likes them.
And I will tell my clients,
...when they do something
that's, like, super awesome,
...that, like,
"I hope that you're proud of you,"
"...because I am very proud of you today."
But again,
...never, never,
[laughs]
...at least me as a therapist,
...I won't give people '100%' or an 'A+',
...because, again, it's not about me,
...I want you to feel proud of you,
...because you see your progress
...not because me as an outsider is, again,
...like, gassing you up or encouraging you,
...um, just for the sake of.
So, yeah.
This was just kind of a quick one.
Like I said, I hope that you guys like this
...or find it interesting or helpful.
If you guys have questions about stuff like this
...or if you have other things
that you would want to know,
...put them in the comments.
I'm happy to keep making videos like this.
But... Yeah, there you go.
That's five things that your
therapist wants you to know.
If you like the video, like the video,
...subscribe to the channel.
We've got a fun mix of content
...and I would love for you to stay
...and watch more of the stuff
...so that we can start a
mental health revolution together,
...and then share the video to help each other grow
...and to help the channel grow.
And that was backward,
...but I don't care enough to redo it.
So I'll see you next Friday.
Okay, bye!
♪♪